Jay Jayabose

Software Engineer

Profile

I'm a software engineer with extensive experience in JavaScript and Ruby and proficiency in TypeScript, Go, and various frameworks. I bring business context and customer empathy from experience working on the business side in early-stage tech companies. Most recently, I built Arbiter, a framework for video conferencing in web applications.

Experience

Co-Creator, Software Engineer

2023 – present | Remote

Arbiter (https://arbiter-framework.com ∂)

- Co-created Arbiter, an open-source, framework that seamlessly integrates room-based video conferencing into web applications and automates deployment to AWS
- Designed, prototyped, and built a video conferencing server (Selective Forwarding Unit) that distributes media streams, and manages call state for 15+ participants in a single room
- Developed a signaling server that enables negotiation of WebRTC connections and synchronizes call state among participants (WebSocket API Gateway, Lambdas, DynamoDB)
- Wrote a RESTful API to manage backend interactions between the frontend application and AWS infrastructure that provisions new ECS container instances to meet user demand (React, HTTP API Gateway, Lambdas)
- Containerized server components and designed a scaling mechanism that reduces complexity of server deployment by 10+ steps and enables API-based scaling (Docker, ECS, Fargate)
- Worked on CLI tool that automates the provisioning of AWS cloud infrastructure (ECS Clusters, WebSocket Gateway, HTTP API Gateway, IAM roles, etc.), reducing a 50+ step workflow to a single command
- Decoupled services based on traffic patterns and resolved race and concurrency challenges associated with eventdriven architecture
- Implemented a pair-programing framework for a remote team of 3 engineers to foster mentorship and collaboration, resulting in increased team-wide ownership of code and clarity on technical decisions
- Authored a comprehensive technical case study providing analysis of Arbiter's problem domain, system design, and engineering decisions (arbiter-framework.com/case-study \mathscr{O})

Software Engineer, Self-employed

2022 - 2023 | Remote

Selected Projects

- DreamCatcher: Tool for debugging webhooks, built with Node.is, Express, MongoDB, Digital Ocean Droplet, Nginx
- Shoply: E-commerce shopping cart, built with React, Node.js, Express, RESTful API, MongoDB
- Donzo: Todo list application, built with Ruby, Sinatra, ERB, RESTful API, PostgreSQL

Commercial operator, Multiple companies

2005 – 2022 | New York, NY

I worked on the business side in startups operating predictive analytics platforms to enable digital media products.

- Contributed to company OKRs and managed a team responsible for 100% of company revenue
- Partnered with product team to develop novel media products for Expedia, Inc.
- · Worked with product and engineering to pivot a 20-person company to a display advertising business
- Managed development of custom direct-response marketing applications for Fortune 500 e-commerce companies

Skills

Languages & Frameworks

Cloud

Other Technologies

JavaScript, Ruby, TypeScript, Go, SQL, HTML/CSS, Node, Express, Sinatra, React, JQuery, Handlebars AWS EC2, ECS, Fargate, DynamoDB, Lambda, HTTP/WebSocket API Gateways, Cloudformation, IAM; Heroku, Digital Ocean Droplet Docker, Git/Github, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Nginx, REST APIs, HTTP, WebSockets

Education

M.B.A., Georgetown University

Washington, DC,